

Social Service Research Centre, National University of Singapore

💌 gcsk1982@gmail.com/gerard@nus.edu.sg | 🎢 gerardchung.com | 🖪 Gerard_Chung | 🕡 gerardchung | 🛅 gerardchung

About me_

I am a research fellow at the Social Service Research Centre, National University of Singapore. I have a Ph.D. in social work from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill School of Social Work. I also practiced as a social worker in a family service center in Singapore.

As a social work researcher, I am interested in researching parenting, family services in the community, and risk assessment. I am especially interested in intervention research and development. With the increased availability of administrative data as a form of BIG data, I am interested to advance the use of admin data in the social service sector to improve social work practices, develop prediction models for risk assessment, and to evaluate social interventions. I also identify as a methodologist where the through line connecting my research interests involved the use of computational social science methods and advanced statistical methods.

Recently, I started various text-as-data analysis projects. See this latest article where I used natural language processing techniques to understand how 1,500 news articles reported about social service agencies during the pandemic in Singapore. I am also extracting textual data from SSAs' annual reports from 2016 to 2022 to look at how directors/CEOs report about their agencies before and during the pandemic. Join my GitHub to follow these projects. My other active work includes two longitudinal studies: Enhancing Positive Outcomes in Youth and the Community and In-Work Poverty and the Challenges of Getting by among the Young.

Research Interests

family services; administrative data; intervention development & evaluation; program engagement; parenting; fathers; risk assessment; child maltreatment; social work processes

Methods

text-as-data; predictive risk modeling; multi-level model; propensity score matching; latent profile analysis; growth curve modeling; structural equation modeling; natural language processing, sentiment analysis, systematic review, meta-analysis

Education

University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill	USA
PHD SOCIAL WORK	2021
National University of Singapore	Singapore
MASTER OF SOCIAL WORK	2016
National University of Singapore	Singapore
Bachelor of Arts (Social Work)	2007
Edith Cowan University	Australia
GRADUATE DIPLOMA IN SOLUTION-FOCUSED BRIEF THERAPY	2011

Grants, Awards, Selections, and Fellowships	
Inaugural Summer Institutes of Computational Social Science in Singapore SICSS	2022
Injury Violence & Prevention Fellowship (US\$3,000)	2021
Injury Prevention Research Center, UNC	
Ee Peng Liang Scholar	2021
Ee Peng Liang Memorial Fund, NUS	

Injury Prevention Research Center, UNC	
Merit Assistantship (4 years funding)	2017
Graduate school, UNC	
Alice Goh Scholarship	2014
NUS	
Work Experiences	
Senior Social Worker, Fei Yue Family Service Centre & Child Abuse Specialist Centre	2008 - 2013
Case management; Groupwork; Clinical supervision; Training	
Research manager 'Strengthening Families Together Pilot', NUS	2014 - 2017
Project manager, Data manager, Data Analyst, Training	
Research Fellow, Social Service Research Centre, NUS	2021 - 2022
Research consultancy, Data analyst, Mentorship, Training	

2020

Publications (First author)

Injury Violence & Prevention Fellowship (US\$3,000)

Authors	Year	Title	Journal
Chung, G., Rodriguez, M. Lanier, P., Gibss, D.	2022	Text-Mining Open-Ended Survey Responses Using Structural Topic Modeling: A Practical Demonstration to Understand Parents' Coping Methods During the COVID-19 Pandemic in Singapore	Journal of Technology in Human Services
Chung, G., Kainz, K., Eisensmith, S., Lanier, P.	2022	Effects of Youth Educational Aspirations on Academic Outcomes and Racial Differences: A Propensity Score Matching Approach	Journal of Child and Family Studies
Chung, G., Lanier, P., Chen, Ding-Geng	2022	What predicts mothers' use of spanking in the first 6 years of early childhood? A latent growth curve analysis	Child & Family Social Work, 27(2), 173–184
Chung, G., Ansong, D., Brevard, K., Ding-Geng, C	2021	Identifying treatment moderators of a trauma-informed parenting intervention with children in foster care: Using model-based recursive partitioning	Child Abuse & Neglect, 117
Chung, G., Smith, Q., Frey, J., & Lanier, P.	2021	Associations Between Depression and Parenting of Fathers in Head Start and Parental Self-efficacy as a Protective Factor	Children and Youth Services Review, 120(105758)
Chung, G., Jensen, T., Parisi, A., Macy, R., & Lanier, P.	2021	Impact of Intimate Partner Violence on Parenting and Children's Externalizing Behaviors: Transactional Processes Over Time	Violence Against Women, 27(14)
Chung, G., Phillips, J., Jensen, T. M., & Lanier, P.	2020	Parental Involvement and Adolescents' Academic Achievement: Latent Profiles of Mother and Father Warmth as a Moderating Influence	Family Process, 59(2), 772–788
Chung, G., Lanier, P., & Wong, P. Y. J.	2020	Mediating Effects of Parental Stress on Harsh Parenting and Parent-Child Relationship during Coronavirus (COVID-19) Pandemic in Singapore	Journal of Family Violence

Publications (Co-author)

Authors	Year	Title	Journal
Lanier, P., Afonso, W., Chung, G., et al.	2022	Demographic, Economic, and Geographic Factors Associated with Uptake of the Earned Income Tax Credit	Journal of Policy Practice and Research
Lanier, P., Rose, R., & Chung, G	2021	A Quasi-Experimental Study of Intensive Alternative Family Treatment to Prevent Entry to Psychiatric Residential Treatment	Child & Adolescent Social Work Journal
Rose, R., Chung, G., Lanier, P.,	2021	Effectiveness of Intensive Alternative Family Treatment on Reducing Re-Admissions to Psy- chiatric Residential Treatment Facilities	Journal of Emotional and Behavioral Disorders, 29(2)
Lanier, P., Jensen, T., Bryant, K., Chung, G., Rose, R., Smith, Q., & Lackmann, L.	2020	A systematic review of the effectiveness of children's behavioral health interventions in psychiatric residential treatment facilities.	Children and Youth Services Review, 113
Lanier, P., Frey, J., Smith, Q., & Chung, G.	2019	A Quasi-Experimental Study of a Peer Support Group to Enhance Protective Factors for Fathers of Children in Head Start	Journal of Child and Family Studies, 28(6), 1558–1570.
Chiu, M., Ghoh, C., Chung, G., & Choi, K. P.	2019	Multistressed families in Singapore: A focus on transnational families	Children and Youth Services Review, 101, 372–382

Publications (In Review)

Authors	Year	Title	Journal
Chung, G., Chan, X. W., Lanier, P., & Wong, P.	2022	Associations Between Work-Family Balance, Parenting Stress, and Marital Conflicts During COVID-19 Pandemic in Singapore	Journal of Child and Family Studies (Under review)
Chung, G., Ansong, D., & Chowa, G.	2022	Effects of Parenting Practices, Goals, and Style on Ghanaian Youth Financial Behavior	Child & Youth Services (Minor revision)
Glatz, T., Lippold, M. A., Chung, G., Jensen, T.	2022	A systematic review of parental self-efficacy among parents of school-age children: A fifteen-year update	Journal of Family Theory and Review (Revise & resubmit)

Publications (In Preparations)

Authors	Year	Title	Target Journal
Chung, G., Ansong, D.	2023	Effects of YouthSave Program: Text-as-data analysis to evaluate treatment effects	Journal of the Society for Social Work and Research
Chung, G., Ansong, D., & Okumu, M	2023	YouthSave Savings Program and Treatment Moderators: A Model-based Recursive Partitioning Analysis	
Chung, G., Lanier, P., Rie, M., Gibbs, D., & Chen, DG.	2023	Risk Factors of Subsequent Allegations of ChildMaltreatment: A Meta-analysis	Child Abuse and Negkect
Chung G., Aloysisus, T	2023	Text-as-data analysis of Social Service Agencies' Annual Reports: Narratives of Directors During COVID-19 pandemic	Social Service Review
Chung G. et al.	2023	Congruency between Fathers' and Mothers' Attachment and Youth Delinquency	Journal of the Society for Social Work and Research
Ng, IYH, Tan, ZH, Chung, G., et al	2023	Precarious work of low wage workers and Impact on Anxiety	
Hyeukung, C, & Chung, G.	2023	Resiliency of children and family functioning: Binational Families in Singapore	
Chung G.	2022	News Representation of Social Service Agencies During COVID-19 in Singapore	Journal of Computational Social Science

(continued)

Authors	Year	Title	Target Journal
Chung G. Aloysius, T., et al.	2022	Meta-analysis: Associations between Parental Attachments and Delinguency	

Research Projects _____

SUMMARY OF RESEARCH PROJECTS

Funder	Project	Year	Role
MSF	Enhancing Positive Outcomes in Youth and the Community	2021-	Researcher
MSF	In-work Poverty Study	2021-	Researcher
UNC	Data Management and Analysis Core Social Stressors and COVID	2020-	GRA
UNC	Creating Community-Designed Approaches for EITC Uptake in Rural North Carolina	2020	Graduate Research Assistant
UNC	Parents as Teachers North Carolina: Impact of COVID-19	2020	CO-PI
_	Parenting during COVID-19 Pandemic in Singapore	2020	PI
UNC	Intensive Alternative Family Treatment for OOHC Youths	2019	GRA
UNC	Illinois Birth Through Three Waiver Demo	2019	GRA
UNC	North Carolina Early Home Visiting Landscape Analysis	2018	GRA
UNC	YouthSave Ghana Savings Program	2018	GRA
UNC	Wise Guys Program Assessment Tool Factor Analysis	2018	CO-PI
AIC	Evaluation of Eldercare Centres	2017	Research Consultant
SOS	National Trends in Suicide SG	2017	Research Consultant
MSF	Early Marriage Prep	2016	Research Assistant
MSF	Strengthening Families Together Pilot	2014	Research Manager

HIGHLIGHTS OF SELECTED RESEARCH (SEE MY **GITHUB** FOR OTHER PROJECTS)

Project	Year	Description	Website
Text-mining news on Social Work Profession in Singapore	Ongoing	Analysis of 7000 news articles from local newspapers in Singapore	https://tinyurl.com/swnewssg
Data Visualizations Text analysis of News on Social Work Profession in Singapore		Vizualizations with SG data Collaborating with SASW	https://tinyurl.com/datavizgerard https://tinyurl.com/swnewssg
Analyzing News on Social Service Agencies in Singapore During COVID-19 Annual reports from SSAs: Analyzing narratives of directors during Pandemic		Analyzing news during panemic on SSAs Text-as-data analysis of annual reports of SSA from 2016-22	https://gerardchung.github.io/ssanews/
Meta-analysis of Risk factors of maltreatment recurrence	2021	Interactive table in Shiny app for results	https://tinyurl.com/metariskfactors
Parenting During COVID-19 in Singapore	2020	Survey of parenting during Circuit-breaker	https://sgcovidparenting.mystrikingly.com
Predictive Risk Modeling of Risk Factors of Child Maltreatment Re-reports	2020	Building a PRM on risk factors of child maltreatment rereports from NSCAW	https://tinyurl.com/prmriskfactors

Presentations _____

1. Chung, G. (2020). Parenting During COVID-19 Pandemic, Ee Peng Liang Memorial Fund, Singapore [Webinar]. https://app.slidebean.com/p/wkeo41g1o6/eplmfpresentationpublic

- 2. Chung, G. (2020). Impact of Intimate Partner Violence on Parenting and Children's Externalizing Behaviors: Transactional Processes Over Time, Methodist Welfare Services FSC, Singapore [Webinar]. https://app.slidebean.com/p/qrymt1a7s2/methodistfscpublic
- 3. Chung, G. (2020). The Impact of Intimate Partner Violence on Parenting, Corporal punishment and Children's Externalizing Behaviors: Transactional Processes Over Time, American Professional Society on the Abuse of Children Conference, New Orleans, USA [Webinar]. https://app.slidebean.com/p/uzqayhuh5z/APSAC2020
- 4. Chung, G. (2020). Parenting During COVID-19, Social Service Research Centre 5thYear Anniversary, NUS, Singapore [Webinar]. https://app.slidebean.com/p/6t09192au8/ssrwebinarpublicshare
- 5. Chung, G. (2020). Mutiple Poster Presentations, Social Work Social Development Conference 2020 [Cancelled due to COVID-19].
- 6. Chung, G., Philips, J., Jensen, T., & Lanier, P. (2019). Parental Involvement and Adolescents' Academic Achievement: Latent Profiles of Mother and Father Warmth as a Moderating Influence, Society for Research in Child Development Conference, Bltimore, USA [Poster {Presentation}].
- 7. Chung, G., Frey, J., & Lanier, P. (2018). A Quasi-Experimental Study of a Peer Support Group to Enhance Protective Factors for Fathers of Children in Head Start, North Carolina Infant/Youth Child Mental Health Association Conference and Annual Meeting [Poster {Presentation}].
- 8. Chung, G., Lanier, P., & Philips, J. (2021). What to Do with Those Open-Ended Questions? Analyzing Textual Data Using Structural Topic Modeling to Understand How Parents Cope during Coronavirus(COVID-19) Stay-Home Orders in Singapore 2021 SSWR Virtual Conference, "Social Work Science for Social Change" [Poster {Presentation}].
- 9. Chung, G., Ansong, D., Brevard, K., & Chen, D.-G. (2021). Who Benefits? Differential Effects of a Trauma-Focused Parenting Intervention for Infants and Children in Foster Care Using Model-Based Recursive Partitioning Analysis: Illinois "Birth through Three" Waiver Demonstration Project 2021 SSWR Virtual Conference, "Social Work Science for Social Change" [Poster {Presentation}].
- 10. Chung, G., Lanier, P., Rie, M., Gibbs, D., & Chen, D.-G. (2021). Risk Factors for Child Maltreatment Recurrence and Re-Reporting: A Meta-Analysis of Studies 2021 SSWR Virtual Conference, "Social Work Science for Social Change" [Poster {Presentation}].
- 11. Chung, G., Lanier, P., & Gibbs, D. (2021). What Works and Who Benefits? Identifying Common Components of Parenting Programs for Children Involved with Child Protection Services: A Model-Based Recursive Partitioning Analysis 2021 SSWR Virtual Conference, "Social Work Science for Social Change" [Poster {Presentation}].

Reports/Articles

- 1. Chung, G. (2022). News Media Representations of Social Service Agencies in Singapore during COVID19 Pandemic A Corpus Linguistics Approach. Snippet, 1. https://fass.nus.edu.sg/ssr/wp-content/uploads/sites/8/2022/03/Snippet_Issue-1_2022_MinorityStress_CommunityConnectedness_NewsMedia_SocialServices.pdf
- 2. Chung, G. (2021). Mediating Effects of Parental Stress on HarshParenting and Parent-Child Relationship duringCoronavirus (COVID-19) Pandemic in Singapore. *Proceedings of NUS Social Service Research Centre 5th Anniversary Webinar Series*. https://fass.nus.edu.sg/ssr/wp-content/uploads/sites/8/2021/06/SSR-5th-Anniversary-Webinar-Proceedings.pdf

Teaching Experience

PRIMARY INSTRUCTOR

Financial Cases: Assessment, case management, and intervention (Academy of Human Development Singapore)

09/2014 - 09/2014

Course design; lectures

Research Skills for Social Service Professionals (SSR)

01/2022 - 01/2022

Course design; lectures

APRIL 2022

Mentoring in Research Skills (SSR)	02/2022 - 04/2022
SMALL GROUP MENTORING; TEACHING	
GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR	
SOWO 918 : Applied Regression Analysis and Generalized Linear Models	01/2021 - 05/2021
Two Guest Lectures; Grading student essays; office hours; supervising student research projects	
SOWO 911: Introduction to Social Statistics and Data Analysis	08/2020 - 12/2020
Lectures; Grading student essays & assignments; office hours; supervising student research projects	
SOWO 911: Introduction to Social Statistics and Data Analysis	08/2019 - 12/2019
Grading student essays & assignments; office hours; supervising student research projects	
SOWO 500: Human Development in Context I: Infancy to Adolescence	01/2019 - 05/2019
Two Lectures; Grading assignments and exams; office hours	
SOWO 800: Evaluation of Social Work Intervention	01/2018 - 06/2018
GRADING STUDENT ESSAYS; OFFICE HOURS; SUPERVISING STUDENT RESEARCH PROJECTS	

Professional Service/Consultancy

RESEARCH CONSULTANCY

- The Samaritans of Singapore SOS (2017-2018)
- Agency for Integrated Care AIC (2017-2018)

AD HOC REVIEWER

- Journal of Child & Family Studies
- Journal of Family Violence
- Child & Family Social Work
- Family Relations
- Interpersona
- Current Psychology
- Infancy
- Canadian Journal of Community Mental Health
- Child & Youth Service Review

EDITORIAL

• Editorial assistant, Asia Pacific Journal of Social Work and Dev (2013-2017)

Social Work Practice Experience

Senior Social Worker, Fei Yue Family Service Centre & Child Abuse Specialist Centre

09/2008 - 09/2013

CASE MANAGEMENT; GROUPWORK; CLINICAL SUPERVISION; TRAINING

References

Mimi Chapman, Ph.D. mimi@email.unc.edu

ASSOCIATE DEAN FOR DOCTORAL EDUCATION; FRANK A. DANIELS DISTINGUISHED PROFESSOR FOR HUMAN SERVICE POLICY INFORMATION, CHAIR OF THE UNC CHAPEL HILL FACULTY, UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL

Chen Ding-Geng, Ph.D. dinchen@email.unc.edu

KURALT DISTINGUISHED PROFESSOR, SCHOOL OF SOCIAL WORK; PROFESSOR IN BIOSTATISTICS, GILLINGS SCHOOL OF GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH, UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL

David Ansong, Ph.D. ansong@email.unc.edu

KURALT EARLY CAREER DISTINGUISHED ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR; FACULTY FELLOW AT GLOBAL SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT INNOVATIONS, UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL

Paul Lanier, Ph.D. planier@email.unc.edu

KURALT DISTINGUISHED ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR; ASSOCIATE DIRECTOR, JORDAN INSTITUTE OF FAMILIES, UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL